Guide to the Nineteenth Century Notebooks, Diaries, and Journals MC.31
New York University Archives
Nineteenth Century Notebooks, Diaries, and Journals
1833-1938
1833-1883
New York University Archives
Torrey, John, 1796-1873
Van Dyck, Ezekiel Deyo
Paton, James Morton, 1863-1944
Houghton, George Hendric, 1820-1897
MacCracken, John Henry, 1875-1948
Ludlum, Charles Henry
Brown, Elbert William
Burroughs, William Frank, d. 1899
Crosby, Howard, 1826-1891
Gould Memorial Library
MC.31
2 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes
The collection contains notebooks, diaries, and journals kept by NYU students and professors from the late nineteenth century. The student notebooks contain the lecture notes taken by five New York University students between 1858-1897. Also included in the collection is Professor John Torrey's diary while traveling in Europe and a sermon journal kept by Professor Howard Crosby.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were transferred from Gould Memorial Library, University Heights in 1973. The accession number realated to this collection is 2019.016.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically in nine series:
I. Charles Ludlum
II. Ezekiel Deyo Van Dyck
III. James Morton Paton
IV. George Hendric Houghton
V. William Frank Burroughs
VI. John Henry McCracken
VII. Elbert William Brown
VII. John Torrey
IX. Howard Crosby
Biographical Note
Charles Henry Ludlum was born in Jamaica, New York, on February 21, 1843. He attended New York University (then the University of the City of New York) College of Arts and Pure Science from 1859-1863 and graduated with an A.B. in 1863. He attended New York University Medical College from 1863-1865 and received his M.D. in 1865. He received his A.M. degree from NYU in 1866. Ludlum was an intern at Bellevue Hospital from 1865-1867, and a visiting physician O.D.D. from 1867-1874. A practicing physician in Boonton, New Jersey, from 1874-1878, he moved his practice to Hempstead, New York, where he spent the remainder of his life. In 1889 Ludlum became a member of the Board of Education of Hempstead and became its president in 1890. He was married to Mary Jane White on May 20, 1868, and had six children.
Ezekiel Deyo Van Dyck was born in New Paltz, New York, on February 15, 1858. He attended New York University's College of Arts and Pure Science from 1876-1880 and graduated with an A.B. degree in 1880. He attended the Union Theological Seminary from 1880-1883 and received his A.M. degree in 1883. Van Dyck was a Presbyterian minister and served the following communities: Carlisle, New York, from 1883-1890; Johnsonville, New York, from 1890-1893; and Greenville, New York, from 1893 on. He married Alida Bevier June 21, 1888, and had four children.
James Morton Paton was born in the city of New York on May 12, 1863. He attended New York University from 1879-1883 and received his A.B. degree in 1883. Paton attended Harvard University from 1883-1887, studied at the American School of Classical Studies at Athens and was a Rogers fellow of Harvard from 1892-1893. He received his Ph.D. from Bonn University in 1894. In 1906, he was a student of classical archaeology in Europe. Paton was a Morton Professor of Latin and French at Middlebury College, Vermont, from 1887-1891. He became an instructor of Greek at Wesleyan University, Connecticut, from 1895-1897, and an associate professor from 1895-1905. He was managing editor of the American Journal of Archeology from 1906-1908, and editor-in-chief from 1917-1920. He died in 1944.
George Hendric Houghton was born in Deerfield, Massachusetts, on February 1, 1820. He attended New York University (then the University of the City of New York) from 1838-1843 and received his A.B. degree in 1842 and his A.M. degree in 1845. He later received a D.D. degree from Columbia University. Houghton was a Protestant Episcopal clergyman who studied theology under the direction of William A. Muhlenberg, while at the same time teaching Greek at St. Paul's College, Flushing, Long Island (1843-1846), of which Muhlenberg was headmaster. He was ordained deacon in 1845 and priest in 1846, and was Muhlenberg's curate at the Church of the Holy Communion in New York until 1847. He ministered to the sick and dying in Bellevue Hospital and devoted his time to the underprivileged, establishing regular religious services at 48 East Twenty-Fourth Street. The parish was organized February 12, 1849, as the Church of the Transfiguration in the City of New York. From 1850-1862, Houghton was also a professor of Hebrew in the General Theological Seminary, New York City. During the Civil War he harbored slaves on their way to the Canadian border, established a war hospital, and during the Draft Riots of 1863 he sheltered hundreds of children driven by a mob from the Colored Orphan Asylum. Houghton's Church of the Transfiguration achieved lasting fame as "the little church around the corner."
William Frank Burroughs received his A.B. degree from New York University in 1859. He died in 1899.
John Henry MacCracken was born in Rochester, Vermont, on September 30, 1875. He attended New York University's College of Arts and Pure Science and graduated with an A.B. in 1894 and an A.M in 1897. He briefly attended Union Theological Seminary in 1894-1895. MacCracken received his Ph.D. from the University of Halle-Wittenburg, Germany, in 1899 and his LL.D. from Westminster College, Missouri, in 1903. MacCracken was an A. Ogden Butler fellow in philosophy in 1894-1895. He became an instructor in Philosophy at New York University and served from 1896-1899, becoming an assistant professor in 1899. He served as President of Westminster College, Missouri, from 1899-1903, and then returned once again to NYU serving as Syndic and Professor of Politics from 1903-1915, which also included one year as acting Chancellor of the University. He became President of Lafayette College in Easton, Pennsylvania and served from 1915-1926. In 1929 he became President of the American Institute of Christian Philosophy, President of the Phi Beta Kappa Alumni of New York, President of the Board at Alborz College in Teheran, Iran and served as a trustee to the American University, Cairo, Egypt and the Masters School at Dobbs Ferry, New York. MacCracken also served as Regional Director of Student Army Training Corps in 1918. In 1927 he was a delegate to the Lausanne Conference, and was a delegate to the Oxford and Edinburough Conferences of 1937. MacCracken was the author of "College and the Commonwealth" (1920). He died in 1948.
Elbert William Brown received his A.B. degree from Yale University in 1865. He was a graduate student attending New York University during the years 1896-1898. He was listed as a student from Flushing, Long Island.
John Torrey was born in New York on August 15, 1796. He later became known as the first professional botanist in the United States. He specialized in the North American flora and is most known for his innovative classification system, known as the "natural system." He often worked with Asa Gray and other notable botanists. In 1858 he founded the Botanical Club of New York, which later became known as the Torrey Botanical Club. During his illustrious career he held several professorial posts beginning at the West Point Military Academy from 1824-1827. In 1832, Torrey arrived at New York University as a professor of chemistry and botany. Later in his life, Torrey served as an Assayer for the United States Mint.
Howard Crosby was born in New York City in 1826. Crosby, after graduating from New York University in 1844, became a Professor of Greek at NYU. After NYU Crosby taught at Rutgers College in New Jersey and in 1863 became pastor of the Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church. Crosby returned to NYU and became its fourth chancellor in 1870 and maintained his pastorship during that time. The eleven years of his administration (1870-1881) marked a period of financial uncertainty and little growth. During his career he published several notable religious works including "The Lands of the Moslem" (1851), "Bible Companion" (1870), "Jesus: His Life and Works" (1871), and "True Temperance Reform" (1879).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains various notebooks, journals, and diaries kept by both students and professors at New York University. The student notebooks provide a useful insight into the lectures and classroom materials presented in the late nineteenth century. John Torrey's diary sheds light on the development of his innovative classification system and would be of interest to scholars studying botanical history. Also included in the collection is a compilation of sermons given by pastor and NYU Professor Howard Crosby.
Universities and Colleges -- Curricula.; New York (N.Y.).; Diaries; Lecture notes.; Pneumatics; Notebooks; Religion -- History; Religion -- Study and teaching; Sermons.; Heat -- Study and teaching; Magnetism -- Study and teaching; Geology -- Study and teaching; Greek literature -- Study and teaching; Philosophy -- Study and teaching.; Mathematics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Optics -- Study and teaching; American poetry; Physiology -- Study and teaching; Physics -- Study and teaching; Church history -- Study and teaching; English literature -- Study and teaching; Archaeology -- Greece; Botany -- Study and teaching; New York University -- Faculty -- 19th century; New York University -- Students -- 19th century; Stevenson, John J. (John James), 1841-1924; New York University; Loomis, Elias, 1811-1889; Draper, John C. (John Christopher), 1835-1885; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849; Martin, Benj. N. (Benjamin Nicholas), 1816-1883; New York University -- Curricula -- History; Baird, Henry Martyn, 1832-1906; Coakley, George Washington; Draper, Henry, 1837-1882; Gould Memorial Library
- Series I: Charles Ludlum, 1860-1863
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of seven notebooks. Most of the notebooks appear to contain verbatim portions of professorial lectures, although some, such as Loomis' Algebra, were copied directly from the course textbook. The notebooks are representative of classes in: Greek Language and Literature taught by Professor Henry M. Baird; English Literature, Rhetoric, and Natural Religion taught by Professor Benjamin N. Martin; Evidences of Revelation taught by Chancellor Isaac Ferris; and Comparative Physiology taught by Professor Henry Draper.
  - Greek Geography: Professor Henry M. Baird and Loomis' Algebra: Professor George W. Coakley, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Greek Language Vol.1: Professor Henry M. Baird, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Greek Language Vol.2: Professor Henry M. Baird, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Greek Literature: Professor Henry M. Baird, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - English Literature, Rhetoric, and Natural Religion: Professor Benjam N. Martin, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Evidence of Revelation: Chancellor Ferris and Osteology: Unknown, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Comparative Physiology: Professor Henry Draper, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II, Ezekiel Deyo Van Dyck, 1878-1880
  Series II contains five notebooks. The student notebooks are representative of classes taught by professors Henry M. Baird and John J. Stevenson spanning 1878-1880.
  - Greek Archaeology and Greek Literature: Professor Henry M. Baird, 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Greek Literature: Professor Henry M. Baird, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Geology: Professor John J. Stevenson, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Geology and Botany: Professor John J. Stevenson, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Geology: Professor John J. Stevenson, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III, James Morton Paton, 1880-1883
  Series III consists of seven notebooks. The notebooks are representative of classes taught by Professors John C. Draper, George W. Coakley, John J. Stevenson, Henry M. Baird, and Albert H. Gallatin.
  - Chemistry, Table of Contents: Professor. John C. Draper, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chemistry Vol. 1: Professor John C. Draper, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chemistry Vol. 2: Professor John C. Draper, 1880-1881 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Trigonometry: Professor George W. Coakley, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Botany: Professor John J. Stevenson, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Geology: Professor John J. Stevenson, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Greek Archaeology: Professor Henry M. Baird, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Physiology: Professor Albert H. Gallatin, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series IV, George Hendric Houghton, 1839-1850
  Series IV includes a journal entitled, "Nugae," a collection of orations and poetry written by Houghton and later presented to G.H. Houghton Butler from an enigmatic "S.H.B." Although several pages have been cut out from the journal, it still contains revealing thoughts and emotions of a young man aged 19 to 30 in early 19th century New York. Of special interest is "The Growth of Freedom", (pp. 1-17) an oration delivered at the University of the City of New York's July 20, 1842 commencement, and the Valedictory Oration (pp. 19-29) delivered the same day. "National Retribution" (pp. 91-101) is the title of an oration delivered in the University Chapel on January 29, 1842. "On Leaving the South-West Turret of the University," (p. 77) written in December 1841, and "On Leaving the University," written in May 1843, expresses in poetical form Houghton's mixed emotions upon graduating.
  - Houghton, George H.: Orations and Poetry, 1842-1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Valedictory Oration, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A Farewell, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - This Too Shall Pass Away, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Epigram, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Voice of the Streamlet, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Shall We Meet In Heaven, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Darkness Filled The Firmament, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Anacreon's Loves, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Response, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Hieron, or The Call To Rest, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Unwritten Thoughts, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Son of Jonas, Lovest Thou Me?, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Cypress and the Lily, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To Anne, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The River's Tale, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Mountain Oak, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Burning Of Moscow, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - On Leaving The South-West Turret of the University, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Meeting of the Sons of Abraham, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Art, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Alcanzor and Layda, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Night Hath Cast Her Mantle O'er Me, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - National Retribution, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Path To Heaven, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To Miss C.D., 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - An Unbidden Song, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To One Departed, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fragment, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Bird of the Drooping Wing, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Clusters and Cycles in Literature, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Stricken of the Herd, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Heaven, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Repentant, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Curse of the Memory, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Mission of the Roman Empire, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Child On Its 3rd Birth-day, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Weep Not For The Dead, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A Song, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Orphan's Prayer, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Love and Beauty, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Watch of Selene, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A Good Night, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Friend, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - God Himself Shall Dry Thy Tears, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Kaleidoscope, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - De Advintu Et Exitu Metae, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To M.41., Cupid Wounded, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Lydian Stone, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Tell Me Lephyr, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Virtue and Vice, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - From Hesiod, From Homer, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Stream, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Maiden, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To Lais - With A Rosebud, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Midas' Epitaph, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - I Am Weary, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - (page cut, title unknown), 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Painter (pages cut), 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Nurse, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - An Evening Hymn, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - A Promise Redeamed, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Friend, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Three Wishes, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Died (obituary), 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To My Guardian Angel (pages cut), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Holy Innocents (from a Sermon), 1849 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Our Lord's Childhood, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Ascention, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Little Eugenia - who died August 1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lines, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - On The Late Secession of a Somewhat Notorious Author, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Frey Zyolenia, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Three Wishes, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Song, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Horace (pages cut), 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Halcyon, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Odes Of Sappho, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Beloved Maiden, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To A Rich, But Ignorant And Unpoetic Woman, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To Venus, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Song, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Serpent-slain Eagle, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ad Amicum Carissimun, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - On Leaving the University, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Mother Fold Me To Thy Breast, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ad Umbras Puellarium Trium, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - An Angel From Heaven Such Honor Accord, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - An Allegory, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - When The Wind And The Tempest, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - I'm Hastening To My Father, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - I Would Go Where Hedron Floweth, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Evening Hymn, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Gift Of The Heart, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To My Mother, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Twelve Apostles, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Lavarium at Pompeii, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Maiden Alethe, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Rose, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Golden Censer, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jesus, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Prayer For Mary, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Holy Week, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - My Prayer Has Been For Thee, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To Alethe, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To Mary, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jerusalem, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - To My Sister, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - We Have Decked Thine Holy Shrine, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sonnet de Des-Barreaux, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Doxology, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Jesu Miserre, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cara Epitaph, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Cara, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The White Robed, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Self, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Peace, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ad Meipsum, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Ad Jesu Christum, Nobis Exemplar, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Renunciation, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Bonum Est, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Heart Come Home, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Tongue Refrain, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Eyes Be Closed, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Mrs. Ballard, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Antithesis, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nuage: Orations and Poetry photocopies, 1839-1850 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series V, William Frank Burroughs, 1858
  This series contains one student notebook covering the Lectures on Natural Philosophy delivered by Professor Elias A. Loomis in 1858. Included in the notes are sections on pneumatics, acoustics, heat, magnetism, and optics.
  - Natural Philosophy: Professor Elias A. Loomis, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 1, PNEUMATICS, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 1, Diving Bell, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 1, Principle of the Air Pump, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 1, Valves, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 2, Exhaustion of the receiver, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 2, The Condenser, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 3, Magdeburg Hemispheres, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 3, The Barometer, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 5, Different Forms of Barometers, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 6, Maiotte's Law, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 6, Observing the boiling point of water, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 8, The Suction Pump, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 8, The Forcing Pump, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 8, The Fire Engine, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 9, The Syphon, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 10, ACOUSTICS, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 11, Theory of waves in liquid bodies, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 12, Velocity of sound, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 13, Theory of echoes, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 14, Musical Sounds, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 15, Vibrations of strings, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 16, Musical Chords, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 17, Vibrations of thin plates, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 18, Organ of Voice, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 19, HEAT, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 20, Air Thermometer, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 21, Conduction, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 22, Latent Heat, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 23, The Pulse Glass, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 24, The Steam Engine, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 25, High Pressure Engine, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 26, Watt's Double Acting Engine, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 27, Definition of Horse Power, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 28, MAGNETISM, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 29, Austral fluid and Boreal fluid, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 30, Magnetic Waves, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 31, Terrestrial Magnetism, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 32, Declination, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 33, Intensity of terrestrial magnetism, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 34, OPTICS, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 35, Reflection of Light, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 36, The Kaleidoscope, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 37, Mirrors, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 38, Refraction of Light, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Lecture number: 39, Axis of a lens, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series VI, John Henry MacCracken, 1892-1893
  Series VI contains the student notebook of John Henry MacCracken which includes the 1895 lecture of Professor John J. Stevenson on Physiology and the 1893 lecture of Professor Henry Mitchell MacCracken on Church History.
  - Notes on Physiology: Professor John J. Stevenson and Lectures on Church History: Professor Henry M. MacCraken, 1892-1893 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series VII, Elbert William Brown, 1897
  Series VII consists of a single notebook. The cover of the notebook had a date of November 1897 and includes the notes of the lectures delivered by instructor John Henry MacCracken on Philosophy.
  - Philosophy: Professor John Henry MacCracken, 1897 (Box 4, Folder 2)